var questions = [
  // CONTRACTS
  {
    "question": "Your software company is selected to develop a bespoke software programme for a small insurance firm. You agree with your client to contract for this work in two phases: the first, a time and materials (T&M) contract for a short scoping exercise at the beginning of the project to agree a work plan; and the second phase a fixed price contract for the actual development work.",
    "color": "green",
    "subquestions": [
      {
        "question": "a) Explain the difference between a T&M and Fixed Price contract;",
        "answer": "Time and materials: Payment is based on number of hours/days worked and expenses incurred. It is more typical for consultancy than for software development.  Risks are shared between client and supplier. Fixed price contract: A fixed amount is agreed for the complete work - quite common in software development. The supplier usually charges a fixed price premium because he takes most of the risk."
      },
      {
        "question": "b) Why it is of benefit to you AND to your client to contract in this way?",
        "answer": "The advantage to you of contracting in this way is because at the outset, you can validate the scope of the project before committing to a fixed price.  This will allow you to validate requirements and develop more accurate cost estimates and schedules.  This reduces the risk to you in entering a fixed price development phase (where you will bear the full risk). You agree a T&M contract for the initial work because you are unfamiliar with the clients requirements and working environment, so are unsure of how long you will need to spend on the scoping, and a T&M contract will ensure you get paid for all the time you spend, so is less risky.  For the client, contracting with you for a small T&M scoping project will allow him to identify any ambiguity or uncertainty around requirements, and therefore will result in a more accurate specification and plan. Agreeing a fixed price for the development phase provides certainty around cost and scope of the deliverable."
      },
      {
        "question": "c) During the development phase, the client asks for a new function, not specified in the original requirement. How do you deal with this contractually?",
        "answer": "You invoke the change control procedure, which you have specified in the contract. This specifies how changes are managed, and how they are priced and scheduled."
      }
    ]
  },
  // CHALLENGES IN SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT
  {
    "question": "Challenges in Software Development",
    "color": "yellow",
    "subquestions": [
      {
        "question": "a) Why do you think information systems are poorly understood by the public?",
        "answer": "Information systems are the most complex artifacts yet built, they are a comparatively recent discipline and are mostly very abstract. For example a rail control system is mostly 'invisible'. Before PCs/Internet, most public use was limited (e.g. ATMs)"
      },
      {
        "question": "b) List three reasons why information systems are important in modern society.",
        "answer": "Information systems are the most complex artifacts yet built and are essential to modern society in a number of ways, such as, Health and well-being; Security; Commerce; Entertainment; Transport; Productivity"
      },
      {
        "question": "c) Describe the two most important causes of information systems failure in your opinion, and give two examples of high profile IT project failures, indicating what went wrong.",
        "answer": "Failure on information systems happen quite often, in fact, it is debatable that information systems projects fails more often then succeeds, two of the most important reasons for informations systems failure are poor communication and engaging in projects that are over ambitious. Two good examples of high profile IT project failures are the National Programme for Information Technology (NPfIT) held by the NHS and the Transfer and Automated Registration of Uncertificated Stock (TAURUS), held by the London Stock Exchange, costing billions and millions respectively to their stakeholders."
      }
    ]
  },
  // SOFTWARE ENGINEERING PROFESSION
  {
    "question": "The IT Profession",
    "color": "purple",
    "subquestions": [
      {
        "question": "a) What are the key characteristics and functions of a profession in the UK? List some of the professional bodies in computing in the USA and the UK.",
        "answer": "A profession exists to provide confidence around the quality of the service delivered, particularly in matters of life and death. Specifies training requirements for members; Controls entry to profession; Provides accreditation for related activities; Specifies and enforces a code of conduct for members; Acts as an advisor on related matters; Defines and publicises good practice and new developments. Some of the professional bodies in computing in the UK and USA are the IEEE, the IET and the BCS."
      },
      {
        "question": "b) Describe what is meant by a reserved title when used in the context of a particular profession, and provide an example. Describe what is meant by a reserved title and function, and provide an example.",
        "answer": "A profession may reserve the title, meaning that one cannot call oneself that title unless registered with the appropriate professional entity, for example, only those registered with the Architects Registration Board can call themselves architects. The same applies for a job function with the exception that instead of carrying the title, one cannot carry out the duties of the given job without being registered for example only members of the Institute of Chartered Accountants and Association of Certified Accountants can audit company accounts. A combination of both title and function may also be reserved, for example, in the UK, one must be registered with the Royal College of Veterinary Surgeons (RCVS) to call oneself a vet, and to carry out surgical procedures on animals"
      },
      {
        "question": "c) Describe clearly the pros and cons for regulation of the software engineering profession.",
        "answer": "Pros: Many IT systems are mission critical, so it would help prevent disaster; It would introduce best practice  and improve IT quality; It would provide a basis for standard training and accreditation; It would provide assurance to customers; It would help the profession mature; It’s necessary to have professional status to attract the best talent; It would provide a central register of qualified SEs; Cons: Most software is not mission-critical; It would drive SE underground or offshore – with potential loss of quality; It’s hard to agree a standard career path or qualifications for a computer; It would reduce number of SEs – so more project delays and increased cost; It would stifle innovation; The SE industry is doing well enough without regulation!; It would be hard to enforce – lots of software engineers have not had formal training;"
      }
    ]
  },
  // FREEDOM OF INFORMATION
  {
    "question": "Freedom of Information",
    "color": "blue",
    "subquestions": [
      {
        "question": "a) What is the purpose of the Freedom of Information Act 2000? In the UK, who does it apply to? What bodies does it exclude?",
        "answer": "Freedom of Information legislation is designed to make public organisations more open and accountable. It gives the right to access to information held by most public authorities and applies to: central and local government departments; the NHS; education authorities; military services, and so on. It excludes the Intelligence services and parts of the BBC."
      },
      {
        "question": "b) List five of the 'absolute exemptions' from the Act.",
        "answer": "Information that is accessible by other means; Information relating to or dealing with security matters; Information contained in court records; Where disclosure of the information would infringe parliamentary privilege; Information held by the House of Commons or the House of Lords, where disclosure would prejudice the effective conduct of public affairs ; Information which the applicant could obtain under the Data Protection Act; Information where release would breach the data protection principles; Information provided in confidence; When disclosing the information is prohibited by an enactment; incompatible with an EU obligation; or would commit a contempt of court"
      },
      {
        "question": "c) What are the grounds for complaint under the FoI Act?",
        "answer": "The grounds for complaint under the FoI Act are: Not responded the request in a timely manner; Does not give proper advice and help; Does not give information in the form requested; Does not explain properly reasons for refusing request."
      },
      {
        "question": "d) Where can one typically find information about an organisation’s commitment to the FoI Act? What are Birkbeck’s obligations under the FoI Act?",
        "answer": "Every public authority must make some information available as a matter of routine through a publication scheme. For Birkbeck, a publication scheme is both a public commitment to make certain information available and a guide to how that information can be obtained. It contains information about how to file Freedom of Information requests and the associated process. It also contains information about how to make a complaint."
      },
      {
        "question": "e) Doc Sportello is a private individual who wants to know more about the Gravity Rainbow project, a high value UK trade deal to sell rockets to the Ruritanians. This has been widely reported in the press, although the sale is still being debated in Parliament. Can the FoI Act help Doc?",
        "answer": "Doc Sportello could apply for a Freedom of Information request but would probably be refused due to affecting public relations a harm based exemption as well as a absolute exemption for its disclosure may infringe parliamentary privilege and conduct of public affairs."
      },
      {
        "question": "f) Provide some guidance to Doc Sportello about what response Doc can expect from the Gravity Rainbow project and under what circumstances Doc can complain if he is unhappy with the information provided.",
        "answer": "Based on Environmental Information Regulations, Doc can expect information about decisions, policies and activities that affect the environment including water, air, fauna, flora, soil, land, energy, noise, waste, emissions. Doc can complain if the Gravity Rainbow project does not: Respond in a timely manner to his Freedom of Information request; Give proper advice and help; Give information in the form requested; Explain properly reason for refusing request."
      },
      {
        "question": "a) What are the qualified exemptions for the Freedom of Information Act?",
        "answer": "Subject to a public interest test. Class based exemptions: Information intended for future publication; Information that relates to communications with members of the Royal family; Information relating to conferring of honours. Harm Based Exemptions: likely to prejudice international relations; likely to prejudice the economic interests of the UK; likely to prejudice law enforcement"
      }
    ]
  },
  // DATA PROTECTION
  {
    "question": "Data Protection",
    "color": "red",
    "subquestions": [
      {
        "question": "a) Describe four of the principles that underpin data protection legislation in the UK.",
        "answer": "Personal data shall be processed fairly and lawfully and in particular shall not be processed unless (a) data subject has given their consent and (b) for sensitive data has given their explicit consent, meaning that it has to be clearly consent, failing to tick an opt-out box is not sufficient; Personal data shall be processed in accordance with the rights of the data subjects, meaning that Data controllers must tell the Information Commissioner what data they are collecting and the purpose for which it is being collected; Personal data shall be adequate, relevant and not excessive in relation to the purpose or purposes for which they are processed, meaning that Data that is not needed can’t be collected, for example shops collecting a customer’s address when not delivering goods; Personal data shall be accurate and, where necessary, kept up to date, this is can be hard to do, for example, universities find it hard to keep student addresses up to date"
      },
      {
        "question": "b) What does the Privacy and Electronic Communications Regulations 2003 cover, as regards telecommunication network and service providers only?",
        "answer": "Privacy & Electronic Communications Regulations 2003: protects a citizen’s right to “privacy”. As regards telecommunication network and service providers, it covers: processing of electronic data; location data and billing data; calling or connected line identification; directories of subscribers; security of telecommunications services"
      },
      {
        "question": "c) What does the Privacy and Electronic Communications Regulation 2003 cover? What do the amended regulations say about website cookies?",
        "answer": "Privacy & Electronic Communications Regulations 2003: protects a citizen’s right to “privacy”. It covers rules on related areas including use of cookies, telephone directories, traffic, location data and security breaches. The amend on the regulation imposes more stringent obligations upon website developers regarding cookies (awareness, purpose, consent)"
      },
      {
        "question": "d) Which UK agency is responsible for data protection?",
        "answer": "Compliance with the Act is regulated and enforced by an independent authority, the Information Commissioner's Office, which maintains guidance relating to the Act."
      },
      {
        "question": "e) What is Internet governance and what types of issues is it concerned with? Which bodies oversee Internet governance?",
        "answer": "Internet governance is the development and application by Governments, the private sector & civil society, in their respective roles, of shared principles, norms, rules, decision-making procedures, & programmes that shape the evolution & use of the Internet. It is concerned with: Infrastructure (Domain Name System, IP addresses); Security, safety and privacy (e.g. abuse, spam, cyber crime); Intellectual property and international trade (including copyrights); Development Issues (particularly developing countries). The bodies which oversee Internet governance are: Internet Governance Forum (IGF); United Nations Working Group on Internet Governance (WGIG); Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers (ICAAN); Internet Watch Foundation (IWF)"
      },
      {
        "question": "b) Define Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act 2000 (RIPA) and what it is intended for",
        "answer": "Protects against unreasonable intrusion  of electronic communication and provides for privacy of communication. Intended to ensure that the relevant investigatory powers are used in accordance with human rights. For each power, the Act covers: the purposes for which they may be used; which authorities can use the powers; who should authorise each use of the power; the use that can be made of the material gained; independent judicial oversight; a means of redress for the individual. The powers are: interception of communications; acquisition/disclosure of communications data; intrusive surveillance (on residential premises/in private vehicles); covert surveillance in the course of specific operations; use of covert human intelligence sources (agents, informants, undercover officers); access to encrypted data"
      }
    ]
  },
  // INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY
  {
    "question": "Intellectual Property in IT",
    "color": "orange",
    "subquestions": [
      {
        "question": "a) What is Intellectual Property (IP) (provide some examples)? What are the three ways in which IP can be protected in the law?",
        "answer": "Intellectual Property is the name given to legal rights which protect creative works, inventions and commercial goodwill. It protects creative works such as Ideas; Books; Music and Algorithms. The three ways in which intellectual property can be protected by law are Patents which protect inventions, formulae, algorithms, and so on; Trademarks which protect manufacturers and suppliers - product names, logos and so on; and Copyright which covers the right to copy a piece of work. One does not need to apply to be protected by copyright, it comes to existence as the new creative work comes to existence. Although not legally as powerful as patents, copyright lasts for 70 years. Patents are a powerful way to protect intellectual property, one must apply for patent, they are costly and take time to be processed. Patents generally work in a first come first served basis and last for 20 years."
      },
      {
        "question": "b) In bespoke software development, who owns the IP? What are the exceptions?",
        "answer": "Depends on the contract agreed between supplier and customer, customer usually gets the copyright but there may be proprietary elements for which the developer retains copyright; There may be open-source elements; There may be third party products in the build (copyright owned by the third party); Developer may keep copyright and sell customer a licence to use"
      },
      {
        "question": "c) You are an employee of Softco, a company that develops a bespoke funds transfer software application for a bank. Your role is to develop the code for the module that calculates commission; you do this by using a combination of custom and open-source code, and your work is acknowledged as an original and valuable contribution. In this situation, describe how ownership of IP is assigned. Do you have a claim to IP?",
        "answer": "Depends on the contract agreed between the developer and Softco, customer usually gets the copyright but there may be proprietary elements for which the developer retains copyright and can sell the customer a licence to use; The open-source elements copyright will be stated in their respective licences;"
      },
      {
        "question": "d) Your friend Steve Gates has developed new software to control how printers optimise use of ink. He doesn’t know how to protect his innovation and comes to you for advice. What can you tell him about the pros and cons of copyrighting and patenting software?",
        "answer": "Patents protect inventions, formulae, algorithms, and so on and Copyright covers the right to copy a piece of work. Since Steve Gate's is developing software to control printers, a physical product, depending on jurisdiction, the software could be patented as part of a patentable physical product. Although patents are a powerful protective framework, they are expensive and take time to be processed, making it harder for smaller companies to achieve then for big companies. If the software does not represent a physical product, the software may not be patentable, in which case, smaller novel pieces of the software could be patented individually, such as formulae and algorithms. In the other hand, although less powerful then patents, the software will be automatically protected by copyright from the moment it came to existence. Patents last for 20 years in contrast with copyright which lasts 70."
      },
      {
        "question": "e) Steve’s day job is with Applesoft, and he mentions that he actually developed his new software as a bespoke solution for an Applesoft client, but that the client has told him it has no interest in exploiting this invention. How does this colour your advice for Steve?",
        "answer": "Copyright generally goes to the author, however, since this piece of software was developed for a client, unless stated in the contract, the client has the right to retain the copyright for the software. An amendment to the contract between the client and Applesoft would be appropriate in this situation, since the client does not have interest in retain the rights to the intellectual property, the client would probably agree with transferring the rights back to the developer."
      },
      {
        "question": "f) Can software be patented? What is the difference on software patenting between the USA and Europe?",
        "answer": "In principle, software cannot be patented, although there are software patents, depends on jurisdiction. In the USA, software can be patented if: Software is part of patentable device; Software controls a process that has some physical effect; Software processes data arising from the physical world. In Europe the position is unclear, and there is no uniform practice across countries. European Union draft Directive on the Patentability of Computer-implemented Inventions has been discussed in order to harmonise the interpretation of the national patentability requirements for computer software-related inventions"
      },
      {
        "question": "g) In 2010, Google was sued by Viacom for infringement of copyright by its subsidiary YouTube. Discuss the pros and cons of this case, indicating whether - in your opinion - the judgement was fair.",
        "answer": "YouTube won the case based on the Digital Millennium Copyright Act (DMCA), which essentially means that ISPs, aggregators and social networking services can`t be held responsible for copyright infringement as long as they take reasonable steps to address the issue once it\'s flagged-up by the copyright holder. One of the reasons for choosing this is because they had implemented hashing technology to block videos that have already been removed. Youtube bought a licence to Finger printing technology that scans all videos before they are uploaded and this referenced against a library for participating copyright owners. They can monitor/ track uploaded videos and monetize the content by allowing advertising to run along side it."
      },
      {
        "question": "h) Your friend has put together an album of family photos that she wants to put on Facebook. She’s used a U2 song as a background music track for the album slide show. What advice could you give her about this? What is YouTube’s position on copyright infringement?",
        "answer": "In 2010, YouTube won the case based on the Digital Millennium Copyright Act (DMCA), which essentially means that ISPs, aggregators and social networking services can't be held responsible for copyright infringement as long as they take reasonable steps to address the issue once it's flagged-up by the copyright holder. Strictly speaking, your friend does not hold the copyright to reproduce the U2 song, however, based on intellectual property fair usage regulations the usage could be possible providing it meets the following factors: purpose and character of the use, including whether such use is of a commercial nature or is for non-profit educational purposes; nature of the copyrighted work; amount and substantiality of the portion used in relation to the copyrighted work as a whole; effect of the use upon the potential market for or value of the copyrighted work."
      },
    ]
  }
];
